Guide to the Northwest Tribal Oral History interviews 1963-1973
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
- Audio Recordings, 1963-1973; Series I; 33999
  - Louie Wapato, Colville (Part I), interviewed by Jeff Wilner, 1973 May 15 (Box 1, Tape 9)
    Tape 9, Side One: Jeff Wilner introduces Louie Wapato. Louie Wapato introduces himself. He speaks about living on his family's original allotments and tending the apple orchards that his family began after the European expansion into their lands. Louie Wapato speaks about the uses of apples, and the raising up of apple orchards. Louie speaks about the early relations between the white people and the Native Americans. Louie speaks about the formation of the Colville reservation on land that was not particularly desirable to the white people at that time, who had already colonized the Colville Valley. He speaks about the mineral property rights of the Colville people. He gives a brief history of the Colville reservation land. The effects of the gold rush, and the minimizing of Colville land by the Federal government during the Allotment Act. Louie speaks to the derisive effects of the Wheeler-Howard Act (Allotment Act). Louie speaks about his role during the Wheeler-Howard Act hearings. He worked as an interpreter. Louie speaks about his grandfather, where he lived and his orchard. Louie speaks about how his grandfather traded for horses and canoes at The Dalles. Louie recalls Barnaby, who was a powerful Colville. Louie speaks about the qualities of an Indian chief in the early days as compared to what his people require from a chief in modern times. Louie speaks about past chiefs, Qe'mý'ekin who was Paloose etc. Wilner asks about other leaders of the Colville. Louie names a few.
    Tape 9, Side Two: [Recording is poor] Louie speaks about state taxation on tribal lands. Louie speaks about Judge John Marshall. Jeff Wilner asks about the 1920's before the New Deal. Louie speaks about the State's oppression of the Indian people. Louie speaks about the Commercial Club that use to be responsible for tribal affairs before the Colville had a business council in the 1910s and 1920s. Louie recalls traveling to Washington DC during the New Deal times and speaking to Emmens and Zimmerman, the assistant commissioner, and Secretary of the Interior. Jeff Wilner asks about the history of the Moses Allotments along the Columbia River. Louie speaks about the removal of the Indians from their traditional homelands along the Columbia River. Louie recalls Long Jim opposing the allotments in favor of a reservation. But the people were forced into taking individual allotments. Louie's wife tells why they were called Moses Allotments. Moses was the chief at the time U.S. officials forced the Indians to take up on allotments. Louie describes the delegation of allotments and tribal land. Louie attests to the Indian ownership of the river bottom and ore beneath it. This ownership was opposed later by the State. Jeff Wilner asks why the Medhows didn't like Moses. Louie and his wife speak about Moses' claim to the Medhows' land that caused friction. Louie's wife speaks of Moses' tyranny as a leader. Louie claims that it was Moses' father that was tyrannical. Moses' death fighting the Blackfeet. Louie's wife speaks about the take over of Wapato Point. She describes ownership practices from a Native perspective: it's the tribe that controls land not the individual. Louie speaks about State taxation on tribal lands. Jeff Wilner asks about Chief Tenasket. Louie recalls Chief Tenasket. Louie speaks to the familial nature of the chief's position, where there are certain family lines in a tribe who breed chiefs. Jeff Wilner asks about Sosopkin from Loomis. Louie speaks about Sosopkin leaving for Canada.
  - Louie Wapato, Colville (Part II), 1973 May 15 (Box 1, Tape 10)
    Tape 10, Side One: Jeff Wilner asks about Chelan Bob. Louie attests to him being his uncle. Chelan Bob was a Wenatchee Indian. Louie speaks about the Colville Reservation once being the Grant Reservation designed for many different tribes in the Eastern Washington area, and thus bringing his uncle from Wenatchee. Chelan Bob married Long Jim's sister. Louie described Chelan Jim. Louie speaks about the "real" Yakamas who only reside now in Nespelem. He claims the Yakama living on the Yakama Reservation are "imported" from the Columbia River basin. He claims the "real" Yakama were massacred by white colonizers. Louie speaks about some of the traditional camping places for Indian people. Louie speaks about his grandfather, the George's, living at Vantage Point along Crab Creek and running cattle. The George's are Moses' people. Louie speaks about being drafted when his father was ill and receiving a delay. Louie's wife speaks about the New Council's meeting where Louie was almost arrested. This was in 1930. Louie recalls some of the first Council people, Pete Gunn, Jim James, etc. Louie, Louie's wife, and an unidentified woman speak about the tribal debate over the New Deal Policies. Louie speaks about the Dam that was built on the Columbia River, and the tribes involvement in the sale of their half of the river bed. Louie attributes the sale of the river bed land to the "half-bloods" that were in control of tribal politics at the time. Louie's wife speaks to how the "half-bloods" gained control of the council. Louie's wife speaks about her father building one of the first orchards. Jeff Wilner asks about the Medhow people. Louie speaks about Moses and Long Jim being forced onto the reservation. Louie's wife speaks about the death of Wapato John's grandson who was a baby when he fell from a horse on its way to the reservation. This was during the Indian removal time. Louie recalls the relocation of the Nez Perce to Nespelem.
    Tape 10, Side Two: Blank
  - Joe Louie, interviewed by K. Lee and Judy Thompson, 1973 May 24 (Box 1, Tape 11-11A)
    Tape 11-11A, Side One: Joe Louie introduces himself as a Nooksack and describes his people's territory. Born in 1894, near Lynden. Father's name is Louie Saq'wel'ti, Mother's name is Annie. She was Nooksack and part Skagit. Recalls the first white settlements in Lynden, the first saw and shingle mills. Joe Louie speaks about his father's renown as a hunter. His father was contracted to hunt for funerals and gatherings. Joe Louie speaks to learning to hunt from his father. Hunts for his people, not for money. Speaks to the Native value of giving. Indian way of live is to offer. Speaks to the loss of this value for the sake of modernism. Treaty of 1855. The Nooksack were not a party to the Treaty due to the harsh winter weather, which made the river non-negotiable. White settlers began to take up homesteads on Nooksack land. Nooksack people couldn't take homesteads until 1884. Joe Louie recalls the traditional burial practice of placing the dead in trees. Homesteads where taken by white people on these burial grounds. Some on traditional spiritual beliefs. The white people that took the homesteads with burials didn't know what to do with the bones scattered on their property. After the Indian Homestead Act, Joe Louie's grandfather, father, and others worked to gather the bones and place them in a cemetery in Northwood. Joe Louie speaks about the way of life of the hunter. A hunter receives an invitation to provide for the people. A hunter then must prepare by understanding life. A hunter must hunt for a death. The search for the animal that is willing to give itself up. Joe Louie laments the fact that Indian parents do not teach their children about the real way of life, do not provide a true education. Education does not lead to acceptance within the white world for an Indian.
    Tape 11-11A, Side Two: Joe Louie speaks about sending a young Indian man to college and his eventual non-acceptance in a predominantly white firm. Joe Louie speaks about the importance of obtaining an education in the Indian way. Joe Louie speaks about meeting with Dr. Webb and discussing education. Joe Louie speaks about the problem of Indian homestead land that has too many heirs to be claimed without a cooperative sale of the land to the tribe. The Federal government disallows this practice, and the land remains unused due to family conflict. [Tape shuts off briefly] Joe Louie speaks about being confined to a reservation. Failure of the current programs to meet immediate needs for the elderly, and those not fit to work in jobs off the reservation. Joe Louie speaks about having to go to the Lummi Reservation for health services. Joe Louie speaks to working towards Indian autonomy from the Federal government. Speaks about building up farms for the Indian people to work. Joe Louie speaks about obtaining tribal recognition for his Nooksack people. He speaks about working with Dr. Reinhart at Western Washington University. Transcript available.
  - Joe Louie, Nooksack (Parts I and II), interviewed by Jeff Wilner, 1973 June 1 (Box 1, Tape 12)
    Tape 12, Side One: Jeff Wilner begins by asking about the Wheeler-Howard Act (Allotment Act), and the negative attitudes towards it by the Indians. Joe Louie attests that the Nooksack did not act negatively to the Act. The Nooksack were an organized people. Joe Louie speaks about having no voice in the debate over the Act because the Nooksack were not recognized as a Treaty tribe. Reinhart from Western Washington University helped the Nooksack establish their tribal claim. Joe Louie speaks about the Act being another piece of bureaucracy that was not intended to help the Indian people's immediate needs. Joe Louie speaks about being asked to leave his homestead and move up to the Middle Fork to less desirable land. Some on the Indian Homestead Act as being comparable to Treaty land rights. Joe Louie speaks about being a part of an Indian organization that was active in petitioning for education and health benefits for the Nooksack. Joe Louie speaks about the problems with the programs that are designed to help Indian people. Superintendent Upchurch and Graves. Constitution and bylaws at Lummi and Swinomish. Forrest Kinley's wife as being responsible for drawing up the Constitution at Lummi. Joe Louie speaks about the general acceptance of the Wheeler-Howard Act as a being the result of the need of Indian Tribes for the Federal programs and protection provided under the Act.
    Tape 12, Side Two: [Poor recording] Joe Louie speaks about his desire for acceptance from the white community. Joe Louie speaks about feeling rejected from the churches and schools in the white community. Joe Louie speaks to not caring whether the Federal government recognizes his people as a tribe. He wants the people that surround him in his everyday life to recognize him as an Indian and an equal. Joe Louie speaks about including in the Nooksack Constitution and bylaws the ability for Nooksack relations not on the census to be able to enter the tribal roles. Joe Louie speaks about starting the "small tribe" which served to educate the rest of the Nooksack people on organizing and getting together as a people. Joe Louie speaks about Roy leading the Nooksack. Joe Louie speaks about Bob Davis, who is a Yakama, and is the Chairman of the Nooksack Incorporated, which is Roy's group. Joe Louie speaks about Tom Williams and Ed Roberts who are part of Roy's group. Joe speaks about being a part of Wilfred Cline's group, who are working on the Constitution and bylaws. Joe Louie speaks about Mickey Roberts.
  - Joe Louie, Nooksack (Part III), 1973 June 1 (Box 1, Tape 13)
    Tape 13, Side One: Joe Louie speaks about Mickey Roberts. Joe Louie speaks about Nooksack Tribal political matters. Joe Louie speaks about Mary Hillaire, and her role in Nooksack political dealings. Programs for economic development. Joe speaks about the deleterious effects of fish hatcheries for the river, but the benefits of hatcheries for the employment of Nooksack people. Joe speaks about the need for his people to thank life. Joe tells a story that teaches about thanking life. Joe speaks about the eradication of the cedar tree from over exploitation. Joe speaks about other uses for the cedar product. Joe Louie speaks about the function of the Indian dance as a right of initiation for a young person.
    Tape 13, Side Two: Blank
  - Mrs. Alba Nettie Shawaway, Nez Perce/Warm Springs, 1973 May 8 (Box 1, Tape 14)
    Tape 14, Side One: Nettie is of Týx tribe, which is called Warm Springs now. Nettie speaks her mother and her father's names and tells where they are from. Nettie speaks about who her father was and where he was from. He grew up in Nespelem, and was half Nez Perce and half Warm Springs. Nettie gives both her father and mother's Indian name. Interviewer, Randy Lewis, asks about Klick Relander, who worked with the Warm Springs on the book, Drummers and the Dreamers. Nettie speaks about his[Klick Relander's] faith in Smohalla. Nettie speaks to the evil nature of Smohalla, who as her father tells her, often would tear up the Washat drums and gamble, before he found his faith through death. Nettie speaks to the origin of birth of Smohalla, who was a Wanapum from Priest Rapids. Nettie speaks to Smohalla's resurrection. Nettie attests that Rex Buck took the long house over from the man that took the long house over from Smohalla. Randy Lewis and Nettie discuss losing the long house at Priest Rapids to the wind. Nettie speaks about her husband, Alba, who was half Wanapum and half Yakama. Nettie explains the difference between a "drummer" and a "dreamer." Dreamers or the Wasklik are of the feather dance. Wasklik have more power, like the Shaker Indian doctor. The Washat, or drummers, don't dream, they just believe there is a heaven. Nettie and Randy Lewis list the Indian doctors in the Valley and the surrounding area. Nettie and Randy Lewis speak about the Chinook dances in the winter where Wasklik, or Indian doctors must prove themselves. There are different categories or degrees of Indian doctors, like the strongest would be the Bluejays. Nettie speaks about the preparation that is needed before roots are gathered in the springtime. This is part of Washat. There is the root feast in the spring time, then the salmon feast, and berry feast. Nettie speaks about having a root feast in Wanapum after gathering the roots. Nettie discusses the people involved in the gathering party as well as the doings at night after the gathering of roots. Nettie speaks about peeling the roots and then going to sweat. The next morning the cooking begins early, and everyone in the long house must wear new clothing for the root feast. Nettie explains about the significance of the seven drums for Washa. Randy Lewis concludes that Smohalla was not the founder of Washa, but was more a prognosticator for it. Randy Lewis adds that only those who belong to Washat have the right know about it. Transcript available.
    Tape 14, Side Two: Blank
  - Nez Perce Songs: Root Feast songs, Social songs, Old Religious songs, War songs, undated (Box 1, Tape 15)
    Tape 15, Side One: Tape is damaged due to degradation.
    Tape 15, Side Two: Tape is damaged due to degradation.
  - Moses Language: Sinkiuse, by Randy Lewis (Part I), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 16)
    Tape 16, Side One: The tape contains vocabulary of the Sinkiuse language by Qe'lheshp'eken and his wife Agnes. Included are kinship terms and place names. Colville pronunciations are included also.
    Tape 16, Side Two: More vocabulary. [Poor recording] Place names, toponyms, continue. Various verbs and nouns. Various fishing gear terminology. Many terms for horses. Vocabulary words for modern devices are Indian derivations.
  - Moses Language: Sinkiuse, by Randy Lewis (Part II), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 17)
    Tape 17, Side One: Vocabulary - human body parts. [Recording is good] Other vocabulary words, verbs, adjectives and nouns. Months of the year, etc.
    Tape 17, Side Two: Vocabulary - adjectives and various other types of words. Place names, days of the week.
  - Moses Language: Sinkiuse, by Randy Lewis (Part III), 1973 May 9 (Box 1, Tape 18-19)
    Tape 18-19, Side One: Vocabulary - diseases, modes of travel, horse outfittings.
    Tape 18-19, Side Two: Vocabulary - names of fish species, geographic terms and traditional identities for the people there, birds, insects and shellfish, plants, place names, counting in numbers, and kinship terms.
  - Jim Holy Cross, Cowlitz, interviewed by Karen Cota, 1973 June 30 (Box 1, Tape 20)
    Tape 20, Side One: Introduction to the Cowlitz people by Jim Holy Cross, their distribution, habitation. Upper and Lower Cowlitz are separated, in modern geography, by Ethel, Washington. Jim Holy Cross speaks about his family lineage. Jim Holy Cross speaks about the Cowlitz meetings, which he views as being governed by money now rather than by principle. Jim speaks about the Cowlitz being a non-treaty tribe. Jim speaks about the intent of the Cowlitz Council to reclaim tribal lands. Jim Holy Cross speaks about the two different rolls for the Cowlitz tribe. Jim Holy Cross speaks about the blood quantum issue, at what degree should someone be considered Indian. Jim speaks about living and working with the Suquamish as an alcohol counselor. Jim speaks about the problematic nature of forming a Cowlitz reservation. Jim speaks about being bought off by the Federal government in lieu of official recognition.
    Tape 20, Side Two: Blank
  - Jim McKay and Ramona Morris. interviewed by Bill Clement, undated (Box 1, Tape 21)
    Tape 21: Jim McKay, Lummi Chief and head of the tribal council, and Ramona Morris head of HEW projects at Lummi were interviewed for KVOS-TV in Bellingham, Washington by Bill Clement. Tape was submitted by Bernie Thomas, Lummi, of the KVOS staff.
  - Ramona Morris, interviewed by Raynette Morris, 1973 Spring (Box 1, Tape 22)
    Tape 22: Ramona Morris, Director of Health, Education, and Welfare for the Lummi Nation is interviewed by her daughter, Raynette Morris on Lummi political affairs from 1960-1973, special programs and cultural as well as economic development. Topics covered include; Aquaculture, LIGHT, various councils- their purposes and composition, Lummi by-laws, and educational programs and concerns. Transcript available.
  - Al Charles, Lummi (Part I), interviewed by Jeff Wilner, 1973 April 26 (Box 1, Tape 23)
    Tape 23: Al Charles, Lummi elder, master carver and cultural leader, describes Lummi history. Topics covered include the delineation of the Lummi as opposed to other Coast Salish groups, toponyms (mostly in Xwlemi chosen, Lummi language) and traditional gathering and living areas, longhouse locations, treaty missionaries and educational practices and the effects of the Allotment Act. Note that any Lummi words will be spelled out using the Lummi phonetic alphabet, thus pronunciation will follow according to the rules of the Lummi alphabet which differs from the American English letter-sound assignment. Transcript available.
  - Al Charles, Lummi (Part II), interviewed by Jeff Wilner, 1973 April 26 (Box 1, Tape 24)
    Tape 24: Conclusion to the interview with Al Charles started on tape 23. The tape contains about 7 minutes of material that overlaps with tape 23 and presents no new information.
  - Felix Solomon, Dora Solomon, Angeline Alexander and Aurelia Celestine (Part I), 1973 April 13 (Box 1, Tape 25)
    Tape 25: Topics covered in this interview include traditional fishing- implements, i.e. hooks, nets, weirs, anchors, locations, processing of the catch, i.e. smoking, drying, and butchering; Siowyn, the banning and release of winter dancing (pow-wow); and Dora Solomon discusses traditional floral resources. Lummi words and Skagit words appear in the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Felix Solomon, Dora Solomon, Angeline Alexander and Aurelia Celestine (Part II), 1973 April 13 (Box 1, Tape 26)
    Tape 26: Conclusion to the interview started on tape 25. Topics covered on this tape include: Smokehouse (longhouse) life, treatment of visitors, and Skagit story of how the Creator gave the trees to the people in the beginning (told by Dora Solomon). Lummi words and Skagit words appear in the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Angeline Alexander, Lummi, interviewed by Laurence Thompson, 1969 (Box 1, Tape 27)
    Tape 27: Lummi elder, Angeline Alexander, discusses genealogy. Only about 10 minutes long and most of the names recalled are the Indian names.
  - Angeline Alexander, Lummi (Part I), interviewed by Morrie Alexander and Ann Ware, 1967 January 27 (Box 1, Tape 28)
    Tape 28: Topics covered include Family genealogy (as covered, though in less detail, on tape 27) and the Creation story of how the Lummi became a tribe, Sxweloxt and his brother. Lummi names and words appear in the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Angeline Alexander, Lummi (Part II), interviewed by Morrie Alexander and Ann Ware, 1967 January 27 (Box 1, Tape 29)
    Tape 29: Continuation of interview started on tape 28. Topics covered include the conclusion of the story of Sxweloxt, family genealogy is continued, boarding school education- i.e. the Tulalip boarding school and Cushman, conduct and features of a traditional gathering, and toponyms. Lummi names and words appear in the Lummi alphabet. Transcript available.
  - Angeline Alexander, Lummi (Part III), interviewed by Morrie Alexander and Ann Ware, 1967 January 27 (Box 1, Tape 30)
    Tape 30: Conclusion to interview that began on tape 28. Only about 5 minutes of interview are contained on this tape and the topic of discussion is raiding. Transcript available.
  - Morrie Alexander, Lummi master carver, 1973 April (Box 1, Tape 31)
    Tape 31: Similar to the lectures given on tape 32 and 40, however question and answer periods vary. Lecture given to CES class. Topics covered include: An introduction to the distinguishing features of Northwest Coast Indians, original use and inhabitation of the San Juan Islands, land mammal hunting- including materials and implements, traditional fishing implements- including materials used for making nets, hooks, traps, and weirs, duck hunting, snares, materials used for carving, masks- including who can wear them and when, naming ceremonies- including a description of the process or work involved. Question and answer period follows the lecture. All Lummi words are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet.
  - Morrie Alexander, Lummi master carver (MISSING), 1973 April (Box 1, Tape 32)
    Tape 32: Similar to the lectures given on tape 31 and 40, however question and answer periods vary. Lecture given to CES class. Topics covered include: An introduction to the distinguishing features of Northwest Coast Indians, original use and inhabitation of the San Juan Islands, land mammal hunting- including materials and implements, traditional fishing implements- including materials used for making nets, hooks, traps, and weirs, duck hunting, snares, materials used for carving, masks- including who can wear them and when, naming ceremonies- including a description of the process or work involved. Question and answer period follows the lecture. All Lummi words are transcribed using the Lummi alphabet. Tape 32 does not exist in the collection at CPNWS.
  - Louisa George, Sarah James, Ella Reid, Philoemina Solomon (Harry), Helen Paul, Rosemary Placid and Ernest Paul, Nooksack and Lummi Elders (Part I), 1973 April 27 (Box 1, Tape 33)